בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Today's דף *daf* is we start a new
פרק *perek*, מ"ז mem zayin. *Mem Zayin*. Let's take a look. Back
to what the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* would do. Actually,
we've been more or less on with the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
*Kohen Gadol* for a while and we were talking about moving the
coals aside from the מזבח Mizbeach? *Mizbe'ach*, getting the inner coals, and
this time would be with only a gold shovel. It would not
be, whatever you call it, a fire pan, it would not be
taking one and transferring, but straight with that one. So now he
has shoveled out the hot coals and the next stage is actually
getting the incense and getting that ready to be brought in. So
let's take a look. הוציאו לו hotzi’u lo. את הכף ואת המחתה
*Hotziu lo et hakaf ve'et hamachtah*. They, whoever they are, but you
know, there are other people around, brought out for him the כף
kaf? *kaf*, the spoon, but not really spoon, whatever the... not
shovel.
Anyway, the... what would you call it? Ladle. Okay, ladle. Some type
of a large spoon, a ladle maybe is good. And מחתה Machta...
*machtah* again. מחתה machta, *machtah* before meant fire pan, but here it
means some type of a container that has in it incense. And
basically, what he is going to do is scoop out two handbreadths
of the incense from this מחתה machta *machtah*, from this container, and
transfer it to the ladle. And he'll bring in with the ladle
because he's only bringing in exactly the amount that fits in his
two, in his two hands. So חפן מלוא חפניו mlo chofnav. *chafan
malo chofnav*. He is חופן *chofen*, it's a verb, right? The...
but he scoops up the fill of his two hands ונתן לתוך
הכף *venatan letoh hakaf*. And he takes, so he scoops this up
from the מחתה machta, *machtah*, from the container, and he puts it
into the ladle. הגדול לפי גדלו והקטן לפי קטנו *Hagadol lefi godlo
vehakatan lefi kotno*. The big... a big person according to his bigness
and a small person according to his smallness, meaning there's not a
fixed amount about how much is מלוא חפניו mlo chofnav *malo chofnav*,
it is specifically his handbreadths and therefore it differs for each person.
But he's חופני *chofni* with his own hands.
Yes, he scoops with his own hands and transfers it into the
ladle. Oh, there's incense on his hands actually.
Basically, yes. Okay, yep.
וכך היה מדתו *Vekakh haya midato*.
And that was its size. Now what exactly that phrase is adding,
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. נטל את המחתה natal et
hamachta בימינו *Natal et hamachtah biyamino*. Now the מחתה machta, *machtah* here
goes back to meaning the fire pan. It's a total fun using
the same... using the same word different. He takes the fire pan
in his right hand, ואת הכף בשמאלו *ve'et hakaf bismo'lo*, the ladle
with the incense in his left. And now he's all ready to
bring it into the קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim*. Didn't tell you by
the way where the מחתה machta *machtah* is sitting, the fire pan
is sitting while he's doing this incense thing, but presumably, whatever, he
puts it down on the floor somewhere. And now he picks them
both up and he's ready to go in. Yes, Charlie?
This is rare for a כהן Kohen *Kohen* to use a left
hand for something.
Yes, so we've been talking about that before about what things are
called an עבודה avoda. *avodah*. עבודה avoda *Avodah* can only be בימין
*beyamin*. So we spoke before about the drawing of the lots. Now
this seems to be not problematic in the sense that there's no
question that this is not an עבודה avoda. *avodah*. You know, you
could even ask is the scooping from the top of the מזבח
mizbeach. *Mizbe'ach* an עבודה avoda, *avodah*, right? It did say, you know,
would that בדיעבד *bedi'avad*, would that have been good with a non-כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol*? Because the תורה Torah. *Torah* says, right,
ולקח מלא melo, המחתה גחלי אש מעל המזבח *velakach malo hamachtah gachalei
esh me'al hamizbe'ach*. So he shall take a full fire pan, fires
from on top of the altar. So does that mean he takes
the fires from on top of the altar, or he takes the
fire pan that contains, you know, coals that are from the altar
and he brings it, you know, in? So how much is the
act of taking the coals part of the עבודה avoda *avodah*? That's
unclear. You know, something that has to be בכהן גדול *bekohen gadol*.
Could that be with your left hand? But that's taking the coals.
By then it says, you know, ומלוא חפניו קטורת ktoret. סמים דקה
והביא מבית לפרוכת *umlo chofnav ketoret samim dakah vehevi mibeit laporochet*. He
takes this in. This scooping and the transferring is not clearly not
indicated in the פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim* and one could argue not an
עבודה avodah *avodah*. But it is going to be what Charlie raises,
an important question, because some of those things will require a left
hand. So while the scooping, by the way,
here the תורה Torah *Torah* explicitly allows your other hand, it has
to be the fill of both hands, right? When he's going to
get the burning the incense, it's going to be the fill of
both hands that he's going to release into the fire that uses
his left hand. So there the תורה *Torah* clearly has to allow
the left hand issue. The interesting thing to think is, and maybe
this is what you were asking, is not the scooping of it,
but the actual, now he's got the fire pan in his right
and, whatever you have to be, and the incense in his left,
and there the תורה *Torah* says והביא מבית לפרוכת *vehevi mibeit laporochet*,
he brings them inside. So the... that process is mentioned explicitly in
the verse. We often know that by other things like by the
blood, the carrying of the blood to the altar is an עבודה
avoda *avodah*. You know, I mean for God's sake, the כהן Kohen
*Kohen* gets back and does his final... Change of clothes into the
white clothes just to bring this stuff out. So, you know, so
we would imagine that the act of bringing them in is considered
an עבודה avoda and Charlie correctly points out that the incense was
done with the left hand. So we'll see the גמרא Gemara. will
discuss why that is, but it is definitely worth noting that issue
about the use of the left and what that indicates about whether
it's an עבודה. avoda So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara
מחתה... machta what do you mean the מחתה, machta the fire pan?
Because as we pointed out in the beginning of the משנה, Mishna,
it actually means a container for the incense. It means something different.
תנא ליה, Tana lei, we taught in the previous משנה, Mishna, נטל
את המחתה ועלה לראש המזבח וחתה וירד. natal et hamachta ve'ala lerosh
hamizbeiach vechata veyarad. We taught about a different מחתה machta. that was
used to scoop out the coals. What did you think here that
they brought out the מחתה, machta you know? He already had the
מחתה, machta so it was scooping out the coals. So the גמרא
Gemara says no. התם מחתה דגחלים. Hatam machta degachalim. There are different
מחתות. machtas. There it's a scooper for the coals והכא מחתה דקטורת.
vehacha machta dektoret. It's a different מחתה machta? here. It's something that
scooped out the incense from wherever it was that they made it.
So it's a completely different vessel here and he took it from
the מחתה machta and he took his handbreadths and he put it
in into the into the ladle. דתניא, Detanya, הוציאו לו את הכף
ריקן hotziu lo et hakaf reikan and we have a ברייתא braita
that spells that out. They took out an empty ladle מלשכת הכלים
milishkat hakeilim from wherever the room was that contained the vessels. מחתה
גדושה Machta gedusha and an overflowing or a heaped up scooper or
container של קטורת shel ktoret of incense מלשכת בית אבטינס milishkat beit
Avtinas from the chamber of the house of Avtinas, which is where
they made the קטורת. ktoret. So you see the מחתה machta? here
in our משנה Mishna is a different מחתה. machta Maybe it's not
even, I don't know if it's even a similar looking vessel, but
whatever it was, it was a container that contained the
incense.
Now there's the proof that there is a מחתה של קטורת. machta
shel ktoret. That's the that's the proof.
That's the proof that we're not talking about the מחתה we were
talking about in the previous משנה. Mishna. It was a מחתה filled
of קטורת. ktoret Okay. חפן ומלא חפניו, Chafan umala chofnav, he scooped
out...
so the רישא reisha and the סיפא seifa of the משנה Mishna
use the word מחתה?
Correct. Even in this משנה, Mishna, נטל את המחתה at the last
line goes back to the מחתה of the גחלים. gechalim. It is
quite strange.
So where is the כף?
kaf It's a ladle where he transfers from the specific amount that's
exactly the size of handbreadths into that ladle, and that's what he'll
bring in with him.
So they are calling it a כף kaf, as a מחתה? I
mean...
No. The מחתה is the container that has a large amount of
קטורת ktoret, brought from the room where they made the קטורת, ktoret
to which he scoops out the amount that exactly fits in his
two hands and puts it into the כף, Kaf. which is the
thing that he'll bring in.
Along with the גחלים? gechalim?
Yes. כף. kaf, Now, חפן מלא חפניו ונתן לתוך הכף גדולה לפי
גדלו וקטנה לפי קטנו וכך היתה מדתה. chafan mala chofnav venatan letoch
hakaf gdola lefi godlo uktana lefi kotno vechach hayta midata. Okay, each
one according to their size and this was its size. We'll see
what that means. כף יום הכפורים למה לי? Kaf Yom Hakippurim lama
li? Why do you need the כף, kaf, meaning why don't you
just have a vessel that has the coals and actually have the
incense in your two hands? Okay? Why do you need a separate
a special vessel to carry the incense? Now you're going to hold
it with... well, that's the question. If you're using two hands to
hold the incense,
where are you holding the fire pan? So the גמרא Gemara says,
כף יום הכפורים למה לי, Kaf Yom Hakippurim lama li, מלא חפניו
והביא אמר רחמנא. melo chofnav veheivi amar rachmana. The fill of your
hands and you should bring it in, so bring it in in
your hands. No, משום דלא אפשר mishum delo efshar because it's not
possible to do otherwise.
היכי נעביד? Heichi ne'evid? What do you want this guy to do?
ניעייל Niayeil first bring in the the coals and leave them there
in the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim והדר ניעייל vehadar niayeil and then
come back out and get the incense and bring it back in.
That seems reasonable, have the coals waiting for you when you come
in. No, הובאה אחת אמר רחמנא ולא שתי הובאות. hava'ah achat amar
rachmana velo shtei hava'ot. The Torah only has one act of bringing.
It says ולקח הכהן מלא המחתה גחלי אש מעל המזבח ומלא חפניו
קטורת סמים דקה והביא. velakach hakohen melo hamachta gachalei esh mei'al hamizbeiach
umelo chofnav ktoret samim daka veheivi. Take the coals, take the incense
and bring it. So there's one bringing for the two of them,
not two bringings. So you can't bring them in one after the
other. הובאה אחת אמר רחמנא ולא שתי הובאות. hava'ah achat amar rachmana
velo shtei hava'ot. Okay. נשקליה לקטורת בחפניו, Nishklei lektoret bechofnav, so maybe
here's how you want to do it all at once by keeping
the incense in the hands. Take the קטורת ketoret in your two
hands, in your like in your two palms,
וננחה למחתה עלה venanchah lemachta alah and put the fire pan on
top of it. So you know, if this is the fire pan,
I've got I don't know, maybe I need somebody to help me
do it, but I scoop out my incense, right? And then I
get my fire pan on top of my hands like this and
I bring it in like that. Of course I'd I better hope
the fire pan is is insulated. Yeah, so I don't exactly know.
We spoke before about the handle being covered with leather. You know,
can you cover the bottom with leather as well and insulate it,
you know?
Plus the handle, where's the handle?
Well, you make a short handle or you make the handle pointing
out the other way.
It's going to be very hard to balance the thing because the
counterweight of of the handle.
Yeah, but so you don't make such a long handle. Anyway, let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. Let's bring it in like this.
Okay?
Well, okay, but where... explaining why that was necessary, why you couldn't
have done the alternative. Okay? So let's do that.
This is good though because it prevents the קטורת ketoret, from blowing
away.
That's good too. That's a good point. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, no, כי מטי התם, ki mati hatam, that'll get you into
the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. But when you get there, כי מטי
התם, ki mati hatam, when you arrive there, היכי עביד, heichi avid,
what are you going to do? Because now what you have to
do is you have to get the firepan on the ground and
now you have to in order that you can now release the
קטורת, ketoret, but the firepan is on top of your hands. So
what are you going to do? נשקריה בשיניה וניחתיה למטה. nishkrei bishinei
venachtei lemata.
So maybe use your teeth, get the handle, and go like that
and put it down and then you've got it on the ground
and then you can release it. You can't use your hands. What?
No, וכל אדם לא יהיה באהל מועד. vechol adam lo yiyeh be’ohel
moed. He's going in alone.
I don't think this is an example of Talmudic humor.
No, maybe it is funny, but I think the גמרא Gemara is
seriously explaining why there was a reason, a reasonable alternative. Okay, so
use your teeth now to move it to the bottom, to move
it down the floor. השתא לפני מלך בשר ודם אין עושים כן.
hashta lifnei melech basar vadam ein osim ken. You wouldn't act in
front of a king this way, moving things around with your teeth.
לפני מלך מלכי המלכים הקדוש ברוך הוא על אחת כמה וכמה. lifnei
melech malchei hamelachim Hakadosh Baruch Hu al achat kama vechama. How much
more so can you not act by God this way, in front
of God this way. הלכך לא אפשר, hilkach lo efshar, therefore, it's
not possible to literally keep it in your hands, the קטורת, ketoret.
while you're bringing in the
firepan. וכיון דלא אפשר, vecheivan d’lo efshar, and since it's not possible
to do it that way, עבדינן כדאשכחן בנשיאים. avdinan kedashkachan bi’nesi’im. So
we look for other models and what we know by the נשיאים
nesi’im when they brought their gifts, the twelve נשיאים nesi’im each one
on a different day for the חנוכת המשכן, Chanukat Hamishkan, it says
they brought כף אחת מלאה קטורת. kaf achat mele’ah ketoret.
One כף, kaf, and there's the word כף, kaf, filled with קטורת.
ketoret, So you see from that model that that is the way
you carry קטורת, ketoret, it's in a כף, and therefore we assume
that that's what we are going to do here. Now, that's very
nice, but what it does is, first of all, it raises the
issue as we'll get to about the use of the left hand
and so on, but it also is if you're carrying them both
in, one thing the firepan and one thing the קטורת, ketoret, we're
also going to have to see also that the trick is going
to be, fine, you carry them both in, you put the firepan
down on the ground, I have this filled with the קטורת, ketoret,
this is, I have to get it into both of my hands.
But how do I do that? How do I get something I'm
holding into both of my hands? And I'm going to have to
wind up using my elbows or doing funny contortions. So it also
raises the question of לפני מלך בשר ודם אין עושים כן. lifnei
melech basar vadam ein osim ken. So תוספות Tosafot deals with that
issue
and he says, you know, what you do there is less contortive,
it's less using contortions and it's more using your hands and even
if you have to a little bit maybe use your mouth or
your teeth anyway, well let's take a quick look at תוספות. Tosafot.
He says הוציאו לו. So
תוספות Tosafot says the following: השתא לפני מלך בשר ודם אין עושים
כן. hashta lifnei melech basar vadam ein osim ken. תימה לי, teima
li, והא דאמר לקמן נוטלה בבזך בראשי אצבעותיו, veha d’amar lelkaman notlah
bevazach beroshei etzbe’otav, ויש אומרים בשיניו, veyesh omerim bishinav, when it comes
time to actually transfer, you know into,
you know, what do you call it,
the קטורת, ketores you know you use your fingers to draw it
close or you sometimes use your teeth. So he says היכי עביד
הכי. heichi avid hachi. How could you do that? Again you're using
your teeth. השתא לפני מלך בשר ודם אין עושים כן. hashta lifnei
melech basar vadam ein osim ken. You know, how could you do
that? Here the גמרא Gemara. says you don't do those types of
things. ויש לומר דהתם אינו אלא מושך הבזך אצלו. veyesh lomar dehatam
eino ela moshech habazach etzlo. והבזך אינו מונח באויר אלא על ידו.
vehabazach eino munach ba’avir ela al yado. והוא מונח ומושך אצלו בשיניו
כדי לחפון פעם אחרת. vehu munach umoshech etzlo bishinav kedei lachpon pa’am
acheret. It's not as respectful, it's not as disrespectful. You basically are
holding it in your hands, you're resting it on your arm, you're
just using your teeth as an assist. So that's less disrespectful than
to carry something in your teeth, you know, but it's getting to
be a little funny.
Anyway, it's disrespectful of you to talk a whole sentence with my
mouth full, it's disrespectful of me.
What can I tell you? What can I tell you? אבל תימה
לי, aval teima li, I'm skipping three lines, אבל תימה לי, aval
teima li, לעביד למחתה בית יד ארוכתא. la’avid lamachta beit yad aruchta.
I've got a better way to do it. Make a very long
handle for the firepan. דבלאו הכי אמרינן לעיל דגבי יום הכפורים יד
ארוכה. d’belav hachi amrinan le’eil degabei Yom Hakipurim yad arucha. Anyway we
said we have a long handle. ויעשה לה בית יד ארוכה שתגיע
עד בית השחי. veya’aseh lah beit yad arucha shetagia ad beit hashachi.
Make it so long that you can carry it in your underarm.
ויתפוס אותה בבית השחי. veyitpos otah beveit hashachi. וראש המחתה תהיה מונחת
על ידיו, verosh hamachta tiheyeh munachat al yadav, או על זרועו השמאלי.
o al zero’o hasmoli. וכי מטי לפנים ישלשל ידיו על הרצפה. vechi
mati lifnim yeshalshel yadav al haritzpah. ויסמוך ידיו וינחת מתחת המחתה. veyismoch
yadav veyanach mitachat hamachta. So he says I don't get it. Get
a long handle, you're carrying the firepan under your arm, you're carrying
the incense in here, so who needs to use, and you know
the firepan is here, maybe it's not suspended in air, maybe the
base of it is on top of your hand or on top
of your arm, but it's basically you're also supporting it with the
handle under your arm, you get there, right? You move this away,
you and you lower it down with your body without your teeth,
right? And you lower it straight down to the ground, it's being
supported by the handle in your arm. I got a way you
can do it without your teeth.
So תוספות Tosafot says, ויש לומר כיון דבעינן מלא. veyesh lomar keivan
d’be’inan melo. That's not just about your teeth to use your underarm
to lower it down. So anyways the point is it would have
to be very contorted if you would do it. So therefore you
do two separate things in two separate hands. You don't actually carry
it in with your hands filled with the קטרת. ketoret. But we
are going to have to see how they transfer the קטרת ketoret
from one vessel into two hands and that also will have to
be contorted and we'll have to... is that a word? And we'll
have to see how that's played out when we get there. Okay,
back to the גמרא.
Gemara You have to miss it only a little bit. All right,
פסח Pesach and everything is like...
yeah that says... yeah.
Okay, so נטל את המחתה בימינו ואת הבזך בשמאלו. natal et hamachta
biyamino v'et habazach bismolo. Why?
Why did they have to take
it from the ladle back into his hands again? You put them
from his hands into the ladle.
Right, yes, but the assumption is that
the... exactly, exactly. Right. But the assumption is that when it's the
burning of it, you know, has to be done with ידיו של
כהן. yadav shel Kohen. It's like... I mean I actually see exactly
how it's described in the פסוקים.
But the assumption is right that the ladle is a sort of...
is a, you know, is a concession, is a necessity in order
to convey it, but that the actual עבודה is done with חפנה.
chofna. It's very powerful, the imagery. It just says ונתן את הקטרת
על האש. v'natan et haktoret al haeish. But
you know the assumption is it means he puts it directly, he
puts it
with מלוא חפניו. But, right, this is just a concession, that's not
the actual כלי kli for the עבודה.
And it's very powerful and symbolic. ויכפר עליו. v'yichaper alav.
Things that have to be done with גופו של כהן. gufo shel
Kohen. But no, sometimes obviously he does it through a vessel. You
שחט shacht with a vessel. You do things... you know, you throw
the blood with a vessel. But here the vessel's a concession for
allowing it to be carried. Okay, so נטל את המחתה בימינו ואת
הבזך בשמאלו. natal et hamachta biyamino v'et habazach bismolo. So the firepan's
in the right hand and the ladle with the incense is in
the left. So the גמרא Gemara says יתיבא בארעא וגר בשמי שמיא?
ytiva be'ara v'ger bishmei shamaya? The citizen is on the ground and
the sojourner or the stranger is up in the heavens? Meaning it's
like, you know, it's the exact opposite. The thing that's more important,
the incense, is in the left hand and the thing that's less
important... right, the
coals, is in the right hand. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
זו מרובה וזו מועטת. zu meruba v'zu muetat. One is a lot
and the other is a little. ואפילו בזמן ששניהם שווים, v'afilu b'zman
sheshneihem shavim, even if you've got a כהן Kohen, that has big
hands, so you have the same sort of volume of incense as
you would have of coals because remember we said there were how
many קב kav of coals did we say there were? There were
three קב kav of coals. Right, that's a lot. I don't know
exactly how much but it's a lot. Even if you've got a
כהן Kohen that has large hands and it's the same volume... ואפילו
בזמן ששניהם
שווים כמעשה דרבי ישמעאל בן קמחית, v'afilu b'zman sheshneihem shavim k'ma'aseh d'Rabbi
Yishmael ben Kimchit, like Rabbi Yishmael ben Kimchit who was a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol, with large hands, nevertheless זו חמה וזו צוננת. zu
chama v'zu tzonenet. One is hot and one is cold. And therefore,
I don't know why hot and cold make a difference which you're
carrying, but I would have said what Michael said which is... which
is, you know, nevertheless one is a lot heavier than the other.
One has to be more careful with it too.
If it's hot you have to be more careful then you need
maybe more control. So that's true. That's true.
Okay, so now let's take a look. If you take רשי Rashi
says... so רשי Rashi by the way says מרובה meruba by the
way means כבידה. kveida. So, you know, that it's heavier which also,
you know, you would want to say as well as part of
the difference. Okay, now by the way though it is worth pointing
out that even with those practical issues again, not to... not to
harp on it, but you're taking the one that is the more
important one in the left hand. I mean, you're using the left
hand for a process, an עבודה, you know, whether you call it
an עבודה is a question, but a process that's described in the
תורה. But you have to say that again you don't have a
choice. Look, even if you did it מלוא חפניו literally, you'd be
bring... using your left hand in the conveying of it into the
קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So using of it in this way is
already anyway sort of implicit, you have to be using your left
hand. Okay, now that we mentioned ישמעאל בן קמחית, Yishmael ben Kimchit,
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol with large hands, we're going to talk
about him for a minute. אמרו עליו על רבי ישמעאל בן קמחית,
amru alav al Rabbi Yishmael ben Kimchit, they said about him שהיה
חופן ארבעת קבים, shehaya chofen arba'at kavim, he would have in his
two handwraps four קב, kav, which is bigger than the volume of
the coals which were three קב, kav, במלוא חפניו, bimlo chofnav, in
the fill of his two hands. ואומר, v'omer, and he would say
כל הנשים זרדו, kol hanashim zardu, all women have זרדו... zardu... we'll
see what that means in a minute. ואומר, v'omer, and they would
say... excuse me, ואומר, v'omer, he would say כל הנשים זרדו, kol
hanashim zardu, all women have
זרדו, zardu, וזרד אמא עלה לגג, v'zered ima ala legag, but the
זרד zered of my mother went to the roof, meaning my mother's
was greater than all of them. So what does the word זרד
zered here mean? So, you know, Jastrow says that זרד zered means
like have... have performed valiantly like ואת עלית על כולנה. v'at alit
al kulana. You know, but...
but it's like a generic word that means performed valiantly, but we'll
see the גמרא Gemara actually interprets זרד zered in a more... it's
funny, it seems like זרד zered the גמרא Gemara recognizes as an
ambiguous word. the גמרא Gemara actually interprets זרד zered in a more,
it's funny, it seems like זרד zered the גמרא Gemara recognizes as
an ambiguous word and gives two interpretations for what it means. So
let's see, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. איכא דאמרי, Ika
de-amri, some say בארסא, be-arsa, it means regarding ארסא. arsa. ארסא arsa
is a type of a like a crummy bread or dough.
Oh, not ערס eres as in?
No, no, no. רש״י Rashi refers it to another גמרא Gemara that
uses זרד zered and ארסא arsa as two different types of ways
of making like bread.
וכדרבא בר יוחנן יונתן דאמר רבא בר יוחנן אמר רבי חייא ארסא
יפה לחולה. U-k'de-Rabba bar Yochanan Yonatan d'amar Rabba bar Yochanan amar Rabbi
Chiyya arsa yafeh l'choleh. ארסא Arsa is good for a sick person,
and רש״י Rashi says since pregnant women are often,
you know, of weak, you know, are not in the best physical
shape, so eating this food is good for them. So it means
my mother took care of herself during her pregnancy, she ate right
during her pregnancy, and that's why I turned out to be such
a healthy baby and such a large person and that's why I
have, you know, I'm so big and I have these large hands
and presumably I'm a large person. So the word זרד zered here
the way רש״י Rashi explains it does not just mean my mother
is exceptional. It means זרד zered is specifically a word that's used
as a type of a bread together with the word ארסא. arsa.
And therefore it means it's a way of saying that, you know,
my mother took care of her, you know, took care of herself,
her health so well when she was pregnant. Again, maybe there's like
a double entendre, maybe it both means she's amazing and it has
the and because the word זרד zered also has the sense specifically
of this type of bread. So that's one reasoning, one explanation.
ואיכא דאמרי, Ve-ika de-amri, some say what his reference was, again, either
the meaning or the double entendre of his reference of the word
זרד zered was בשכבת זרד be-shichvat zered regarding
semen. וכדרבי אבהו, U-k'de-Rabbi Abbahu, like רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. דרבי אבהו
רמי, De-Rabbi Abbahu rami, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu shows a contradiction. כתיב,
Ketiv, one verse says ותזרני חיל למלחמה. va-tezreni chayil la-milchama. You God
have like the פשט pshat of the pasuk is you have girded
me with strength for war. But it's using the word ותזרני va-tezreni
זרד zered by the way and also there's like a lot of
alliteration going on, זרד, zered, and also זורה zoreh is to winnow,
right? And so what with a ה? heh? No, I know, but
I'm telling you, you know, alliterations, types of things. זורה Zoreh with
a ה heh is to winnow and what it means is like
the choicest semen. So I was sort of conceived by the, you
know, by the choicest semen. So therefore, I know, I don't know
how his mother made it happen or whatever, she had some control
once it's in there.
Yeah, exactly, she was supposed to.
Well, that's true, that's true, but you know,
I'm so great because of the way my mother took care of
herself, right? Okay, ותזרני חיל וכתיב המאזרני Va-tezreni chayil u-ketiv ha-me-azreni with
an א aleph חיל למלחמה, chayil la-milchama, which girds me. So we
understand the idea of to gird, but what's the ותזרני va-tezreni without
the א? aleph? אמר דוד לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar David lifnei
ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu, so דוד David said before God, רבונו של עולם,
Ribono shel Olam, Master of the Universe,
זריתני, zeritani, you have winnowed me, again, the way רש״י Rashi reads
this meaning that you have, you know, winnowed out the sperm so
that I was conceived by the choicest of the
sperm, וזרזרתני ve-zirzartani and that has sort of, you know, strengthened me.
So anyway, the point being that based on what sperm created the,
you know, led to the insemination, that created me as the wonderful,
strong, good person I am. Right, exactly why he's attributing to his
mother is unclear. רש״י Rashi also points out that the word זרד
zered is a type of a, it's a type of a grain
or a not whatever, a plant that's like long and thin, so
maybe also it relates to somehow symbolically like some type of a
choice, choice sperm.
Okay, and how do you get that from ארסא? arsa?
Not, it's a different explanation. One is זרד zered is a word
associated with ארסא arsa and refers to a type of grain, and
it's about she took care of her health. And the other is
that the word זרד zered is associated with זרע zera and זורה
zoreh and refers to a the choice sperm. Okay, and רש״י Rashi
also says זרד zered is a type of a, of a plant
or something that grows long and thin, so it has the reference
of, it has a different allusion of the choice sperm. Okay, I
thought that ארסא arsa was a play on עריסה arisa as in
like the little bed? That's what I, all right, maybe. I was
thinking about that, maybe.
Okay. אמרו עליו על רבי ישמעאל בן קמחי. Amru alav al Rabbi
Yishmael ben Kimchi.
By the way, it's interesting that it's referred to his mother, what
about his father? So, so they said about רבי ישמעאל בן קמחי,
Rabbi Yishmael ben Kimchi, פעם אחת סיפר דברים עם ערבי אחד בשוק,
Pa'am achat siper devarim im Aravi echad ba-shuk, once he was having
a conversation with a certain Arab in the marketplace, ונתזה צינורא מפיו
על בגדיו, ve-nitza tzinora mi-piv al begadav, and a like stream of
spittle came from the Arab and hit his, hit his clothes. And
basically חז״ל Chazal have, you know, assigned the given the status of
like a זב zav to all non-Jewish men and זבה zavah to
non-Jewish women, which means that any type of spit is like an
אב הטומאה av ha-tum'ah and therefore it made him טמא. tamei. And
so and he couldn't go to the מקוה mikveh just, you know,
immediately and be טהור. tahor. So what happened? ונכנס ישבב אחיו ושימש
תחתיו, Ve-nichnas Yeshevav achiv ve-shimesh tachtav,
and his brother ישבב Yeshevav went in and did the service in
his stead. וראתה אמן שני כהנים גדולים. ביום אחד V'rasah imman shnei
Kohanim Gedolim b'yom echad and his mother saw two כהנים גדולים kohanim
gedolim on יום כיפור Yom Kippur together at the same time like
in her life or maybe literally on the same day. So רש״י
Rashi says it was יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. The מהרש״א Marsha says
it's a little hard to imagine he was talking, he took a
little break from the עבודה in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
went out to speak to some Arab. So he says maybe it
was like ערב יום כיפור. Erev Yom Kippur. But it means, so
if it was ערב יום כיפור, Erev Yom Kippur, could have been
any day of the year meaning I mean okay maybe it means
that his brother served on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and then he
went back because maybe it wouldn't have been a big deal if
his brother served as the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol you know, on
Wednesday in the middle of a week. You know, so if it's
significance that her mother had a son as another son as a
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol it wants to assume יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
You could have said it has nothing to do with יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. But somehow some at least if this
is ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur and he's just been a
טבול יום, Tevul Yom, right? Then he couldn't have done it on
like יום כיפור Yom Kippur day?
Yeah, so that's why I don't exactly get right maybe it means
that he didn't have a kins before nightfall, you know, something like
that.
Yeah, but he's called to illustrate how he could manage so much
weight of incense- well,
we started because he's so big and how he had this big
קטורת Ketoret and so on, but now we're talking about stories about
him.
But I agree with Michael, first of all what's he doing anyway?
Isn't he supposed to be a week separate from people leading up
to יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? He's also leaving the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash in by- and to talk to some
stranger the מהרש״א- Marsha so I don't get why it has to
talk about יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Maybe it just means his mother
had two sons serve as כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gedolim on the same
day even not יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But anyway רש״י Rashi has
it on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
Yes, תוספות Tosafos says ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that this is an Arab
king and therefore had to come out and speak sort of- that's
what רש״י Rashi says.
No, Arab king? Yes,
ראיתי בש״ס ירושלמי, ra'iti b'shas Yerushalmi, talk with the king? No, כהן
גדול halo-
it has nothing to do with an Arab king. It's just anyway
we're not up to that yet, we're not up to that yet
and it's not about an Arab king. Let's do רש״י. Rashi. Okay,
so that's story one. ושוב אמרו עליו על רבי ישמעאל בן קמחית,
V'shuv amru alav al Rabbi Yishmael ben Kimchis, they also said it
about רבי ישמעאל בן קמחית. Rabbi Yishmael ben Kimchis. פעם אחת יצא
וסיפר עם אדון אחד בשוק, Pa'am achas yatza v'siper im adon echad
bashuk, once he left to speak to some right great personage outside.
ונצצה מפיו על בגדיו V'nitz-tzinah mipiv al begadav and again he was
hit by this spittle and now he's טמא. tamei. ונכנס יוסף אחיו
ושימש תחתיו V'nichnas Yosef achiv v'shimesh tachtav and I don't know what
happened to his other brother who last time took his place.
No yeah because once you're elevated one day, right? and then aren't
you sort of in limbo?
Yeah, but then couldn't you serve when the כהן גדול again becomes
disqualified? So anyway, now his other brother went to serve in his
stead. וראתה אמן שני כהנים גדולים Ve-ra'atah imman shenei kohanim gedolim. ביום
אחד b'yom echad and again his mother saw her two sons as
כהן גדול on the same day. Of course it's pretty funny at
the expense of her first son. It's like this joke that these
two Jewish women are talking says oh, you know, what tell says
hasn't seen each other for a while so whatever happened, you know,
to your daughter? So Miriam said oh well, you know,
she married this lovely doctor 20 years ago. Oh so wonderful. She
says yeah but they got divorced. He says אוי נעבעך. oy nebach.
He says yeah but then she married this other wonderful guy, a
lawyer. Oh so wonderful. He says yeah but they got divorced too.
She says but then she married this other guy, you know, and
I don't know what would it be like a you know a
businessman. Oh yeah but they got divorced too. She says your daughter,
she married a lawyer and a doctor and a businessman, so much
נחת nachas from one child.
So anyway,
I think I told the joke a little wrong but you get
the idea. Anyway, so you have so much
נחת, nachas, three כהנים גדולים. Kohanim Gedolim. Okay anyway, but the מהרש״א
Basha is a little bothered by the way of matching up these
כהנים Kohanim with the if you remember the list of the כהנים
גדולים Kohanim Gedolim before. Anyway, he points out that there it
mentioned a Rabbi Yishmael by the father's name. So he suggests that
the reason here it's mentioning it by the mother's name although we're
going to tell another story about the mother is that maybe she
the three כהנים גדולים Kohanim Gedolim who all brothers were all brothers
by the same mother but not by the same father. So really
it is all being connected to her and that ties into the
next story as well, so let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanna
Rabbanan, we taught in ברייתא: barisa: שבעה בנים היו לה לקמחית, Shiva
banim hayu lah l'Kimchis, she had seven sons.
וכולם שימשו בכהונה גדולה, V'chulam shimshu bikshuna gedolah, they all- so maybe
seven times a lot of spit or some of them one died
or whatever. So and again the מהרש״א Marsha says that it was
her that was attributed to not the father. Maybe it were different
fathers. אמרו לה חכמים, Amru lah chachamim, so the sages want to
know what it was about her: מה עשית שזכית לכך? Mah asis
she-zachis l'kach? What did you do that you merited having so many
sons that were all כהנים גדולים? Kohanim Gedolim? אמרה להם Amar lah
she said to them: מימיי לא ראו קורות ביתי קלעי שערי. Miyamy
lo ra'u koros beisi kil'ei sa'ari. From my never in my days
the beams of my house never saw the braids of my hair,
meaning I never even took off my hair covering even inside the
house. אמרו לה, amru lah, so they said back to her: הרבה
עשו כן ולא הועילו. Harbeh asu kein v'lo ho'ilu. Many others did
that way and it didn't do them any good. So it's quite
fascinating because this is often quoted as
ideal for women about this whole issue about covering their hair and
צניעות, tzniut, and as we know, there is some people go really,
really overboard about stringencies around צניעות tzniut and about the weight of
women's responsibility about that, and this גמרא Gemara is often quoted, look
at this as the ideal and tell of seven sons כהנים גדולים
Kohanim Gedolim in the תורה and even inside of her house and
so on. So the question is right, what do you do with
the response back? Is the response back
like yes, that's a wonderful thing, but there's got to be other
things going on as well because this doesn't do it all by
itself? Or is the response back like no, that can't be what
it's based on because other people do it and they don't get
the same result? So that's what you think it's based on, just
because you think that's what you're so great about you, doesn't necessarily
mean that objectively that's correct, that that's what's so wonderful and that's
what led to this.
Okay,
yes, according to this המאירי haMeiri says that השם Hashem decides what
the proper reward is for every woman who does that.
Right. Okay, there is...
but does this also mean if she was... when she was a
married woman or even when she was single?
Right, could be even single, that's an interesting other discussion. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, the Rabbis taught: בקומצו. Bekumtzo. So
that is in his... now this is going about a similar act
but not the double hand-breadth, but the single hand-breadth that's taken from
the מנחה mincha when you offer up the קומץ. kometz.
והרים ממנו בקומצו מסולת המנחה ומשמנה. Veherim mimenu bekumtzo misolet hamincha umishmena.
Yeah, this is about a normal מנחה.
mincha. Correct, a normal מנחה, mincha, we're doing it as a point
of comparison. So a normal מנחה mincha the hand-breadth is taken and
offered up and then the rest of the מנחה mincha is eaten.
תנו רבנן בקומצו. Tanu Rabbanan: Bekumtzo. שלא יעשה מידה לקומץ. Shelo yaaseh
midah lekometz. Do not, you cannot actually say, "I'm going to measure
out how big my hand-breadth is, I'm a כהן, I'm going to
measure it out, and from now on I'm not going to actually
dirty my hands and scoop it out physically with my hands from
a מנחה, mincha, I'll just scoop it out with this pre-assigned כלי
kli that's exactly the right volume." No, you can't do it, because
it says והרים ממנו בקומצו. Veherim mimenu bekumtzo. You take out of
the מנחה mincha with your hand, with your hand-breadth, not the size
of your hand-breadth, but with your hand-breadth, you actually have to use
your hand itself. שלא יעשה מידה לקומץ. Shelo yaaseh midah lekometz. איבעיא
להו. Ibaia lehu. So they asked a question. מהו שיעשה מידה לחפינה?
Mahu sheyaaseh midah lechafina? Can you, do you have to actually scoop
out, this is similar to your question Jonathan, but at the other
end, at the beginning, do you have to actually scoop out the
stuff initially with your hands, or if you know the volume of
your two hand-breadths when you do the initial scooping out, maybe you
could do it with a vessel? Maybe you don't have to do
an act of scooping it in order to bring it in. איבעיא
להו מהו שיעשה מידה לחפינה. Ibaia lehu mahu sheyaaseh midah lechafina. Can
you do, make a vessel that's the size of your hand-breadth, and
why should that be different? התם דכתיב בקומצו, Hatam dechtiv bekumtzo, because
by the מנחה mincha it says literally with his hand, with his
hand-breadth. אבל הכא דלא כתיב בחפניו, Aval hacha dela ktiv bechofnav, and
it doesn't say you shall take with your hands. What does it
say? מלא חפניו, Mlo chofnav, the fill of your hands. So it
could be the amount that fills your hands without actually scooping it
out
yourself. קטרת סמים דקה, Ketoret samim daka, no, you don't have to
actually use your hands in the scooping. אי נמי, Ei nami, or
do we say, יליף מלא מלא? Yalif mlo mlo? מקומצו, Mikumtzo, we
make a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah because elsewhere it says בקומצו, bekumtzo,
it says ומלא קומצו. umlo kumtzo. It says,
מה הפסוק אומר? Ma hapasuk omer? וקמץ משם מלא קומצו. Vekamatz misham
mlo kumtzo. And here it says מלא חפניו. mlo chofnav. So even
though it says the fill, we can learn out from the link
to the קומץ kometz that it means with his hands itself, you
have to do the scooping. So what's the story? תא שמע. Ta
shma. From here.
וכך היה מידתה. Vechach haya midatah. And this after saying big person
big amount, small person small amount, says, "this was the measure." So
what's that extra phrase mean, "this was the measure"? מאי לאו, Mai
lav, does it not mean שאם רצה לעשות מידה אחרת עושה? sheim
ratza laasot midah acheret oseh?
Maybe "this was the measure" means what matters is not the act
of scooping, what matters is the size, and if you had this
measure, that's fine, even if you just measured it out, even if
you didn't use your hands. Maybe that's what the משנה Mishna means.
לא, Lo, no, that's not what the phrase means. הכי קאמר, Hachi
kaamar, here's how you could read the phrase. וכך היה חוזר וחופנה
מבפנים. Vechach haya chozer vechofnah mibifnim.
What it means is, the same way you would do the scooping
outside, when you got back in to the קודש הקדשים, Kodesh HaKodashim,
you'd scoop it out again, okay, and that's what it would
mean. So the
גמרא Gemara says, שמע מינה, Shma mina, can you infer from this
חופן וחוזר וחופן, chofen vechozer vechofen, that you scoop it out twice,
you scoop it out at the beginning and you scoop it out
at the end, because that's how you're reading in this משנה, Mishna,
and we'll see later what the alternative is, right, is the alternative
like Jonathan said, spilling straight from the vessel into the fire, or
maybe the alternative is putting it in your hands but not scooping
it out with your hands, okay, but the way you're reading it,
you're reading that the משנה Mishna saying you scoop at the beginning,
you scoop
at the end. So is that really what... so are you going
to come down on that side? The גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא
שאם רצה לעשות מידה עושה. dilma sheim ratza laasot midah oseh. No,
then I'll say the other... then I'll argue back, maybe it doesn't
mean scooping, maybe it means you can use a measure without doing
scooping. אי נמי שלא יחסר ושלא יותיר, Ei nami shelo yechasar veshelo
yotir, or... means is, it has to be exactly the fill of
your hand, no more, no less. Now that's the easiest read of
the משנה. Mishnah. It says the big one according to his size,
small one if you're small, this was the measure,
meaning it had to be exactly this size. Exactly the size of
your handbreaths whether you're big or small. But the גמרא Gemara suggests
two other possible reads of it. Either ככה היה מדתה Kakha Haya
Midata could mean you can use this size even if you don't
do a scooping, or ככה היה מדתה Kakha Haya Midata means the
same way you would scoop when you began, you would scoop at
the end. We'll discuss that later, but the גמרא Gemara says you
can't pin me down to one of those two answers. You want
to prove whether you can use something, whether you can use a
vessel rather than do the scooping, whether you do another scooping or
not, anything you try to argue, I'll say the phrase in the
משנה Mishnah means the other. And you can't pin me down. But
it got now three possible reads of that phrase. Either exactly that
amount, a simple read, or use that amount even without scooping, or
scoop again when you get to the קדש הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. Yes.
You said that the כהן
scoops it out. Yes. Puts it into a vessel. Right. And the
vessel's the size of the hand.
What are we doing now? At the end we're going to take
it, we're going to scoop it out of the vessel. Yes. And
then put it on the fire. But when you scoop it a
second time, you're going to lose something.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to talk about how to do
that about exactly that challenge. It gets labeled as one of the
hardest עבודות avodas in the מקדש. Mikdash. How you can... well what?
No, it's two hands. The מנחה mincha is a קומץ, kometz, the
קטרת ketoret is a מלא חפניו melo chofnav in the plural, two
hands, both, scoop of both. So we're going to discuss that. That's
going to be the whole discussion coming up, how to get it
all back out.
Can you get around the left hand rule
if it's going to go from point A to point B in
a, let's call it a, in a vessel? Yes. A metal vessel.
Yes. So you have your metal vessel. Right. And the vessel you're
putting it on, I'm looking at it as a ladle with a
hook on it. You just hook it on the elbow and you
carry it... you've got everything on the right hand. Right. So when
you get there, you put down your plate, you reach over, you...
So that's brilliant. I was sort of wondering that as well, why
we're only
imagining that you can have a straight handle. Why thinking about using
some type of a hook. I was thinking about like a ring
that you could hold onto, but a hook is even a smarter
idea. Yeah, I don't exactly get why that wasn't a possibility. That's
a...
We don't have to say it wasn't a possibility, they just haven't
described that. They're just saying what if you do it this way
you've got these problems.
Well no, but that explains why you have one in your right
hand, one in your left hand, which is what the משנה Mishnah
says. So I don't know why they did not have the hook
idea. That's a very brilliant idea. Okay, so let's take a look
now. So we don't know if you have to literally scoop it
out the first time or can you just do מלא חפניו melo
chofnav and that amount. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tano Rabbanan, now we're going
to go back to talk about the קומץ kometz by a normal
מנחה mincha a little bit.
מלא קומצו, melo kumtzo, the fill of your handbreath.
יכול מבורץ, yakhol mevoratz, maybe it means
overflowing? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar בקומצו, bekumtzo, with your handbreath, meaning which
is a precise word. As opposed to מלא, the sense of fill
could be even
overflowing. אי בקומצו, I bekumtzo, if it's just with the handbreath, יכול
אפילו בראש אצבעותיו, yakhol afilu berosh etzbeotav, maybe it doesn't fully fill
it up, maybe it's just a little bit that fits under the
tips of your fingers? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar מלא קומצו, melo kumtzo,
no, it has to be a full amount. So you have to
get a full amount, you have to get as much in as
you can in the volume here, but without it
overflowing. כקמצו, kiktzo, מלא קומצו כדקמצי אינשי melo kumtzo kedikamtzi inshi like
people would normally take a handbreath of something. הא כיצד, ha ketzad,
how do you do it? חופה שלוש אצבעותיו על פיסת ידו, chofeh
shalosh etzbeotav al pisat yado, your three middle fingers are folded over
onto the palm of your hand, וקומץ vekometz and you scoop up
into
them.
ובמחבת uvemachvat ובמרחשת uvemarcheshet and
how about if you're scooping from a מנחה mincha that is not
just flour, that is baked? So some type of a fried or
the different frying pans of the מנחה. mincha. So you're having to
scoop stuff up that is hard. Now you would crack it into
halves and quarters and eighths, but you'd still be talking about some
more solid thing rather than something that's more flour. So that you
would have to מוחך בגודלו מלמעלה ובאצבע קטנה מלמטה. mochekh begudlo milmala
ube-etzba ketana milmata. So there you're not going to have it easily
fitting in, stuff will be sticking out. So you have to use
your thumb on the top and your pinky on the bottom to
break the stuff that's on the top and to smooth it out.
וזו היא עבודה קשה שבמקדש. vezo hi avoda kasha she-bamikdash. This was
the hardest עבודה in the מקדש Mikdash to break the stuff and
to smooth it out and get the exact amount into your hands
without getting too
much. The גמרא Gemara says: זו היא ותו לא? zo hi vethu
lo? This was the hardest עבודה and nothing else? פאיכא מליקה, pa-ika
melika, we have a משנה Mishnah that says that doing the מליקה
melika was the hardest עבודה in the מקדש, Mikdash, the... the cutting
the neck of the bird with your with your thumbnail. ואיכא חפינה.
Vaika chafina. We're going to get to, as was pointed out, you're
going to have to re-scoop the stuff and, you know, and get
every little last piece of קטורת Ketoret. back into your hands. That's
going to be labeled as one of the hardest עבודות Avodos of
the מקדש. Mikdash. אלא זו היא מעבודות קשות שבמקדש. Ella zu hi
me-avodos kashos she-ba-mikdash. This is on the list. This is one of
the hardest עבודות, Avodos, not the hardest or not the only hardest.
Okay. אמר רב יוחנן. Amar Rav Yochanan. Rav Yochanan says: בעי רבי
יהושע בן עוזא. Ba'ei Rabi Yehoshua ben Uza. Ben... okay, רבי יהושע
בן עוזא Rabi Yehoshua ben Uza asked the following question: בין הביניים
שמלא קומצו מהו? Bein ha-beinayim she-melo kumtzo mahu? What about the stuff
that's between the fingers of מלא קומצו? melo kumtzo? It's not under...
it's not under your fingers here, it's not sticking out that you
could see it, you know, from with your fist. It's the stuff
that is exactly being held between your two between your fingers. Okay,
the stuff that's right here between your fingers. What's the story? What
is its status? בין הביניים שמלא קומצו מהו? Bein ha-beinayim she-melo kumtzo
mahu? I don't know, I don't know. שמלא קומצו מהו? She-melo kumtzo
mahu? So is that considered to be the קומץ Kometz or is
that considered to be the שירים? Shirayim? Do you burn it or
do you not burn it on the מזבח? mizbeach So אמר רב
פפא מלא קומצו מהו. Amar Rav Papa melo kumtzo mahu. אמר רב
פפא: דגוואי לא תיבעי לך. Amar Rav Papa: De-gavai lo tiba'i lach.
The stuff that's on the inside of the hand, obviously that's not
a question. דודאי קומץ הוא. De-vadai kometz hu. That's definitely the קומץ.
Kometz. דבראי. De-barai. The stuff on the outside, maybe it's sort of,
you know, coming from between your fingers but it's visible on the
outside. So that also לא תיבעי לך. lo tiba'i lach. I don't
even have a question. דודאי שירים הוא. De-vadai shirayim hu. That's definitely
the remnants of the מנחה. Mincha. That's eaten. כי דיבעי לך. Ki
diba'i lach. Again, we're at a מנחה Mincha here, we're not at
the... we're not by the... by the קטורת. כי דיבעי לך. Ki
diba'i lach. My question... the question is דבין ביני. de-vein beini. The
stuff in between, not on the outside, not on the inside. מהי?
Mai? What's the answer?
And so Rav Yochanan said that exact same thing. So why is
Rav Papa repeating it?
He's just clarifying,
exactly what's being asked. Okay, so אמר רב יוחנן. Amar Rav Yochanan.
Rav Yochanan says: הדר פשטה יהושע בן עוזא. Hadar pashatah Yehoshua ben
Uza. Yehoshua ben Uza after raising the question finally came to the
conclusion. What's the conclusion? בין הביניים ספק נינהו, Bein ha-beinayim safek ninhu,
that it's a ספק. Safek. Now your response should be, what do
you mean 'came to the conclusion'? He started saying what's its status
and he concluded to say it's a ספק. Safek. I don't know.
So תוספות, Tosafos, very nice תוספות. Tosafos. If you take a look,
תוספות Tosafos says: הדר פשטה בין הביניים ספק. Hadar pashatah bein ha-beinayim
safek. תוספות Tosafos says: לא ידענא מאי קאמר הדר פשטה. Lo yadana
mai ka'amar hadar pashatah. מעיקרא נמי ספיקא איבעיא ליה וספק הוא. Me-ikara
nami sefeika ibayei lei ve-safek hu. It's already said it's a ספק.
Safek. So תוספות Tosafos has a very nice answer. ושמא יש לומר
דמעיקרא מספקא ליה. Ve-shema yesh lomar de-me'ikara mesapka lei. Originally he had
a doubt. דהוה סלקא דעתך למפשטא. De-havah salka daitach le-mipshatah. I thought
I could come out one way or the other. האי בכלל קומץ
או האי בכלל שירים, Hai biklal kometz o hai biklal shirayim, whether
to put it in category A or category B. והדר פשטה דספק
הוא. Ve-hadar pashatah de-safek hu. What was his conclusion? It's a doubt.
Meaning not just, I'll never figure this out, it's too hard for
me, I'll never figure it out. No, what he means that it's
a doubt is, ואין בו לחזור ולפשוט הבעיה אי בדי קומץ אי
בדי שירים. Ve-ein bo lachazor ve-lipshot ha-ba'aya i badei kometz i badei
shirayim. It's no longer a question to me does it fit in
category A, does it fit in category B, אלא בודאי ספק הוא.
Ella be-vadai safek hu. ואין אדם יכול לעמוד על הדבר. Ve-ein adam
yachol la'amod al ha-davar. It's in the category of ספק. Safek. Meaning
a very nice analogy to this is the idea of בין השמשות.
Bein ha-Shemashos. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says: is בין השמשות, Bein ha-Shemashos,
the period after sunset till it gets dark, dusk, is that day
or night? And it says it's a ספק. Safek. So the normal
understanding of a ספק Safek is, it's either day or night we
just don't exactly know what that point of transition is. But Rav
Soloveitchik has a very beautiful piece where he develops the idea, he's
not the only one but he develops the idea, that it's not
that there's some point that's the transition and we don't know exactly
where to pinpoint it. No, this period of after sunset before dark,
dusk, is by definition neither day nor night, it's some type of,
you know, middle zone that's in between day and night, and it
has a halachic status as a ספק. Safek. It's not just it's
one or the other we don't know. Like the גמרא Gemara asks
often, like a כוי. Koy. Right. Is it a חיה, Chayah, is
it a בהמה, Behemah, or is it a בריה בפני עצמה? Beriyah
bifnei atzmah? Right. So תוספות Tosafos says והדר פשטה Ve-hadar pashatah is,
it's not like I don't know how to categorize it. By definition,
I am categorizing it as as indeterminate. Its status is indeterminate, its
status is is neither, unable to be defined as either one or
the other.
So that's that's an identity, that is an identity.
So now let's see, the גמרא Gemara. is going to say, so
what do you do? So let's take a look. Okay, so he
says like
this. Back in the גמרא. Gemara. So back in the גמרא. Gemara
So the גמרא Gemara says: היכי עביד? Heichi avid? So what can
you do? So אמר רבי חנינא: מקטיר קומץ לחודיה. Amar Rabi Chanina:
Maktir kometz le-chudeih. So the stuff that's under your fingers, that you
burn up. That's definitely the קומץ. Kometz. תחילה. Techila. That you burn
first. והדר בין הביניים. Ve-hadar bein ha-beinayim. And then after you've burned
that, then release the stuff between your fingers and burn that. Now
why? Why do you do it in that way? So obviously the
stuff between your fingers you want to burn because it might be
the קומץ Kometz and then you have to burn it. But why
do you do it in two stages? דיאמרת בין הביניים ברישא. Di-amart
bein ha-beinayim be-reisha. We'll talk about that too. דיאמרת בין הביניים ברישא.
Di-amart bein ha-beinayim be-reisha. If you say first you burn the stuff
that's between your fingers or at the same time with the קומץ,
Kometz, then you got a problem.
Maybe they're שיריים. shirayim. So why is that a problem? דהוו להו
שיריים שחסרו בין קמיצה להקטרה Dehavu lei shirayim shechasru bein kemitzah lehaktara
because then it would mean that before you did the הקטרה, haktara,
you finished the הקטרה, haktara, some of the שיריים shirayim was lost.
So forget the fingers. Let's imagine I take the קומץ, komitz, I
have my leftover מנחה mincha here, and some of it spills, and
some of it gets ruined before I burn my קומץ. komitz. So
the הלכה halacha is, you can't go ahead and burn the קומץ.
komitz. The קומץ komitz can only be burnt if there's a full
amount of the שיריים. shirayim. דאמר מר, De'amar mar, and we teach,
שיריים שחסרו בין קמיצה להקטרה, shirayim shechasru bein kemitzah lehaktara, if some
of the שיריים shirayim get wasted, lost, between the act of the
taking of the קומץ komitz and the burning of it, אין מקטירין
עליהם את הקומץ, ein maktirin aleihem et hakomitz, you can't burn the
קומץ. komitz. תוספות Tosafot actually points out there's a debate. Some say
the whole מנחה mincha is פסול, pasul, some say if you burn
the קומץ komitz you won't be able to eat the שיריים. shirayim.
But either way, it's a problem. And therefore, if I burnt everything
at once, then that would be, or certainly if I burnt between
the fingers first, but I imagine even if you burnt it at
once, then when the הקטרה haktara is being burnt, we don't have
the full amount of the שיריים. shirayim. And therefore you have to
first release the stuff that's definitely the קומץ, komitz, let that be
burnt so you have the full amount of שיריים shirayim when that's
being burnt, and then you release the remainder that's between your fingers.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
now it asks Michael's question. אי הכי, Ei hachi, fine, I get
why you do that in two stages. But now the flip case
is you might be burning stuff that's the שיריים. shirayim. הכא נמי
אי קרי כאן כל שממנו לאישים הרי הוא בבל תקטרו, Hacha nami
i karei kan kol shemimenu le'ishim harei hu be'val taktiru, anything that's
from which it you took the stuff that goes on the fire,
meaning anything that is the שיריים, shirayim, you're not allowed to burn
on the מזבח. mizbeach So you're not allowed, you can't burn on
the מזבח mizbeach, the שיריים. shirayim. There's a biblical prohibition of לא
תקטירו ממנו אשה לה', lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem, which חז"ל Chazal
say apply to the remnant of the מנחה. mincha. So how are
you allowed to burn it on the מזבח mizbeach. if this might
be the שיריים? shirayim? אמר רב יהודה בריה דרב שמואל בר פפא,
Amar Rav Yehuda berei de'Rav Shmuel bar Papa, דמקטיר להו לשום עצים,
demaktir lehu leshum eitzim,
when you burn it on the מזבח, mizbeach. you don't burn it
as as as קומץ. komitz. You're saying, I'm now releasing the stuff
between my fingers and this should be treated just like fuel for
the מזבח. mizbeach. Fuel. I'm not doing it as a- I'm not
being מקטיר maktir it, I'm not offering it up as an offering
on the מזבח. mizbeach? בל תקטירו, Bal taktiru, which is an איסור
issur to do with the שיריים, shirayim, I'm just putting it on
for fuel. And we know that that is able to recategorize it.
כרבי אליעזר, Ke'Rabbi Eliezer, like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, דתניא, detanya,
we taught in the ברייתא, Beraita, רבי אליעזר אומר לריח ניחוח אי
אתה מעלה, Rabbi Eliezer omer lereyach nicho'ach ee ata ma'aleh,
right?
So this is the הלכה halacha about a similar case. You have
limbs of a חטאת chatat that got mixed up with limbs of
an עולה. olah. What do you do? So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says you burn it all on the מזבח. mizbeach. How can you
burn it all on the מזבח? mizbeach Well the limbs of a
חטאת chatat are not allowed to be burnt on the מזבח. mizbeach,
So he says no, the only prohibition is to burn them לריח
ניחוח lereyach nicho'ach
based on the verse. It says אל המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח.
el hamizbeach lo ya'alu lereyach nicho'ach. And then it says and so
in this issue about what you're not allowed to burn, it emphasizes
to bring up for a pleasing smell. So he says that's why
you can offer them up and categorize it differently. לריח ניחוח אי
אתה מעלה, Lereyach nicho'ach ee ata ma'aleh, you can't burn this stuff
that needs that should be leftover, the limbs of a חטאת, chatat,
the remnant of a מנחה, mincha, you can't burn it on the
מזבח in the context of an offering, of לריח ניחוח. lereyach nicho'ach.
But- wait one minute,
it's ויקרא ב', Vayikra beis, לא תקטירו ממנו אשה לה' והמזבח לא
יעלו לריח ניחוח. lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem ve'hamizbeach lo ya'alu lereyach
nicho'ach. אבל אתה מעלה לשום עצים, Aval ata ma'aleh leshum eitzim, you
can offer them up as a type of a firewood. So the
גמרא Gemara says, הניחא לרבי אליעזר, Hani'cha le'Rabbi Eliezer, fine, that's Rabbi
Eliezer that gives you this way of getting it on the fire.
Call it that it's not an offering, call it
fuel. אלא לרבנן מאי איכא למימר, Ella le'rabbanan mai ika lemeimar, but
for the rabbis, your designation doesn't matter, and so how can you
offer this up? אמר רב מרי דקמצי שמנה, Amar Rav Mari de'kamtzai
shamnei, fine, get fat people to do the קמיצה. kemitzah.
There's no solution, so the only way to do it is do
get the person who does the קמיצה kemitzah to have so much
like flesh and whatever that nothing is going to get between their
fingers.
Which is
what- like the guy from-?
Yeah! What?
Quite the contrary.
Yeah, between
your fingers.
Yeah, I don't know. השתא דאתית להכי, Hashta de'aseit lehachi, now that
you've given that answer, רבי אליעזר נמי דקמצי שמנה, Rabbi Eliezer nami
de'kamtzai shamnei, even Rabbi Eliezer only allows you to make it fuel
if you have no option, but of course we would prefer it
that you do the קמיצה kemitzah and there is no stuff between
the fingers and the גמרא Gemara somehow thinks that if you get
a fat person it helps. I do want to say one thing,
we'll end here, but
I do want to say just one thing about this about you
do it for firewood, you give it the designation of firewood, because
if you're giving it the designation of firewood, then if it really
is the קומץ, komitz,
then how is it considered a legitimate הקטרה? haktara? If it really
is the קומץ. komitz. So א', aleph, you have one of two
options. א', aleph, you could say if it really is the קומץ,
komitz, then it doesn't matter what you designate. If objectively it was
קומץ komitz and being burnt on the מזבח, that's that's good regardless
of your כוונה. kavanah. Or what רש"י Rashi says, which is what
Michael says, which is you stiff... Wait. If this is the קומץ,
komets, I want it to be for the sake of the קומץ.
komets. If it's the שייריים, shirayim, I want it to be firewood.
Or שיירה. sheyara. Now that idea that you can stipulate what your
intent is is ברירה, breira, which is questionable, right? We often say
that you stipulate things, but that's not your intent. That's if you
want something to take effect. Like, this sale will take effect if
A is true, the sale will take effect. If B is true,
if it's not true, then it won't take effect. But to define
the nature of what you're doing, like what's your intent, what are
you actually thinking about, how you're relating to it? Well, how I
relate to it is dependent on... no, how are you relating to
it right now? So that idea that you can sort of stipulate
what your כוונה kavana is is somewhat questionable. But that's what רש"י
Rashi says. But again, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say this. The גמרא
just says you do it לשום עצים leshum etzim and maybe even
if it is the הקטרה, haktara, your intent doesn't matter and it
would still be good.
Wait, I'm a little confused. This whole thing about בל תקטירו bal
taktiru is about כל שאר וכל דבש. kol se'or vechol devash. So
how are you getting the המנחה ha-mincha in here?
Right, so because the דרשה drasha is, if you read the whole
פסוק, pasuk, it's the דרשה drasha is קדשי ממנו לאישי. kadshi mimenu
le'ishei.
All right, let's just do that I guess and we'll end with
that. So what's the פסוק pasuk here?
And then we go to the next one on the bottom. Right.
So the פסוק pasuk is right, והנותרת מן המנחה לאהרון ולבניו מאשי
השם, כל מנחה אשר תקריבו ממנה לא תעשה חמץ. vehanoeteret min hamincha
l'aharon ulevanav me'ishei Hashem, kol mincha asher takrivu mimena lo te'aseh chametz.
So as the way it reads is anything that אשר תקריבו, asher
takrivu, anything that is left over,
no, excuse me, לא תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם. lo taktiru mimenu isheh
l'Hashem. If you notice the phrase was קדשי ממנו לאישים. kadshi mimenu
le'ishim. So it means ממנו אשה, mimenu isheh, anything that's from it
you put an offering up on the altar, it was ממנו אשה,
mimenu isheh, and this is what is left over, that is the
בל תקטירו. bal taktiru. So they forget the שאר וכל דבש. se'or
vechol devash. לא תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem
means anything that's from it went up an offering to the altar
and this is what's left over, בל תקטירו. bal taktiru. That's the
phrase of קדשי ממנו לאישה. kadshi mimenu le'isha. Okay, we will end
here. All right. But
what's that? Here, מ"ז.
Does anybody driving need... I'm davening...
Does Rabbi Soloveitchik extend that סברא sevara on ספק safek to every
ספק safek or just to בין השמשות? bein hashmashot?
I mean,
or one or two other interesting things that could fall in that
category, but that's what makes it unusual, you know, that's...